<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet
      title="Calculating CDK Properties">
   <intro>
      <description>
         This tutorial demonstrates how to calculate properties (aka descriptors) with CDK from scripts.<br/><br/>
This is commonly used in QSAR analyses.
      </description>
   </intro>

   <item
         title="Step 1: List available descriptors">
      <description>

		Descriptors in Bioclipse are identified with the Blue Obelisk Descriptor Ontology.
		To list available descriptors, use the command:<br/><br/>
		
         <b>qsar.getDescriptorIDs()</b><br/><br/>

      </description>
      
        <action
			pluginId="net.bioclipse.scripting.ui"
			class="net.bioclipse.scripting.ui.actions.ScriptAction"
			param1="qsar.getDescriptorIDs()"/>
      
   </item>
   
      <item
         title="Step 2: Calculating single properties">
      <description>
         
         To calculate a single descriptor, use the following command:<br/><br/>
         
         <b>qsar.calculate(IMolecule, descriptorID)</b><br/><br/>

		The gist 95194 shows a script to demonstrate this.         
         
      </description>
      
        <action
			pluginId="net.bioclipse.scripting.ui"
			class="net.bioclipse.scripting.ui.actions.ScriptAction"
			param1="res=gist.download(95194,&quot;/Virtual/qsar.js&quot;); ui.open(res); js.executeFile(res)"/>
      
   </item>
   
   <item
         title="Step 3: Calculating multiple properties">
      <description>
         
         To calculate a list of descriptors for a list of molecules, use the following command:<br/><br/>
         
         <b>qsar.calculateNoParams(molecules, descriptors)</b><br/><br/>

		The gist 95189 shows a script to demonstrate this.
         
      </description>
      
       <action
			pluginId="net.bioclipse.scripting.ui"
			class="net.bioclipse.scripting.ui.actions.ScriptAction"
			param1="res=gist.download(95189,&quot;/Virtual/qsar-multi.js&quot;); ui.open(res); js.executeFile(res)"/>
      
   </item>
   
   <item
         title="Step 4: Creating a QSAR Project">
      <description>

			Go to menu <b>File > New... > Other</b> and create a new QSAR Project.			         
         
      </description>
      <command
            required="false"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.newWizard(newWizardId=net.bioclipse.qsar.wizards.NewQSARRProjectWizard)"/>
   </item>
   
      <item
         title="Step 5: Using the QSAR editor">
      <description>

			Double-clicking on the file qsar.xml in the Navigator opens the QSAR Editor. 
			This editor allows for the setup of daaset in a novel file format called QSAR-ML.<br/><br/>

			The tabs at the bottom of the editor allows for specifying data and metadata for the 
			qsar dataset.<br/><br/>
			
			The tab <b>Information</b> allows for adding metadata about the dataset.<br/><br/>

			The tab <b>Molecules</b> contains a list of molecules in the analysis. 
			You can Drag and drop files here from any project and they will be copied into the project.<br/><br/>

			The tab <b>Descriptors</b> contains a list of descriptors in the analysis. 
			Select in the left view and click the <b>Add</b> button. Some descriptors 
			require/offer parameters that can be set in the lower right view.<br/><br/>

			The tab <b>Responses</b> allows for adding response variables to the structures.<br/><br/>

			The tab <b>Sources</b> displays the QSAR-ML source.<br/><br/>

			Note that the dataset is built in the background when you save, 
			if you have at least one structure and one descriptor chosen. The results are cached 
			so it will not be calculated again if already calculated. 
			The calculated values are saved in the QSAR-ML but also in a comma-separated 
			file called <b>dataset.csv</b>.  <br/><br/>
         
      </description>
      
   </item>

      <item
         title="Step 6: Open dataset in Matrix Editor">
      <description>
		Double-click the dataset.csv to open it in the Matrix Editor.
      </description>
   </item>
   
         <item
         title="Step 7: Open the R Console">
      <description>
			If you have R installed, you can access it directly from Bioclipse via the R-console. 
			Reveal the R-console from the menu <b>Window > Show View > Other</b> and select <b>R Console</b> 
      </description>
      <command
            required="false"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.views.showView(org.eclipse.ui.views.showView.viewId=net.bioclipse.r.ui.views.RConsoleView)"/>
      
   </item>

  <item
         title="Step 8: Load the dataset into R">
      <description>

		Loading the dataset into R can be achieved by entering, in the R Console:<br/><br/>
			         
		<b>dataset=read.delim(file="myQsarProject/dataset.csv", sep=",", header=TRUE, row.names=1, na.strings="NaN")</b>
         
      </description>
      
   </item>

  <item
         title="Step 9: Use R to analyze dataset">
      <description>
      
      		Here is a simple example to demonstrate how the read file can be analyzed in R:<br/><br/>

			<b>datasat=as.matrix(dataset)</b><br/><br/>
			<b>mod &lt;- lm(dataset[,1] ~ dataset[,2:ncol(dataset)], na.action=na.omit)</b><br/><br/>			
			<b>plot(mod)</b><br/><br/>
         
      </description>
      
   </item>
   
</cheatsheet>
